Guide to the Louis Isadore Kahn Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Louis Isadore Kahn collection
1951-1978
1962-1977
MS 1345
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.5
The collection consists of publications on or by Louis Kahn and photographs of structures designed by Kahn.
Kahn, Louis I., 1901-1974
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale Center for British Art, 1978, 1997; transferred from the Art and Architecture Library, 1999. Gift of Dale Gibbs, 2004. Gift of Nurur Rahman Kahn, 2005.
Biographical / Historical
Architect; b. Island of Osel, Russia, brought to U.S., 1905, naturalized, 1915; B. Arch., U. Pa., 1924; private practice architecture, 1953-1974; prof. architecture, U. Pa., 1957-1974, named to Paul Philippe Cret chair in architecture, 1966-1971, emeritus, 1971-1974; prof. architecture, Yale, 1952-1957; among his principal works are the Yale Art Gallery and the Yale Center for British Art.
Scope and Contents
This material was collected by the Librarian of the British Art Center at Yale University in the years following the Center's construction. It was transferred to Manuscripts and Archives in 1978 along with 930 prints of architectural drawings of the British Art Center and several original Kahn sketches which were put into the Architectural Archives Collection (YRG 46A).
This unprocessed material is made up largely of publications on or by Louis Kahn covering a span from 1962-1975. The books and articles discuss Kahn's life, art, buildings, and his architecture and design theories.
In addition there is some miscellaneous correspondence and photographs of the Exeter Library, Louis Kahn, British Art Center construction, models, and interiors and a substantial number of photographs of architectural drawings, many of which were used in the production of Jules Prown's book The Architecture of the Yale Center for British Art (1977). The copyright to these photographs is unclear.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Architecture, Modern; Photographs; Architects; Kahn, Louis I., 1901-1974
- Inventory
  - Publications on/by Kahn (Box 1)
    - "Building with Spent Light," Time. 15 january 1973, pp. 60-65. (Box 1)
    - "Within the Folds of Construction," The Architectural Forum. october 1973, PP. 27-35. (Box 1)
    - Entire issue devoted to Kahn, The Architectural Forum. july/august 1972 (Box 1)
    - "Lighting Starts with Daylight," Progressive Architecture. september 1973, pp. 82-85. (Box 1)
    - News release, Yale University News Bureau, by Jules D. Prown. 27 october 1969. "Structure and Form," Louis I. Kahn. The Voice of America Forum Architecture Lecture Series. no date. (Box 1)
    - "Kahn's Kimbell: A building in praise of nature and light," pp. 84-91, no date nor publication indicated. (Box 1)
    - Copy of speech given by Louis I. Kahn on the occasion of presentation of the AIA 1971 Gold Medal, 24 June 1971. (Box 1)
    - Entire issue devoted to Kahn, Global Architectur e, 1971. (Box 1)
    - Wurman, Richard Saul and Feldman, Eugene, eds. and designers. The Notebooks and Drawings of Louis I. Kahn. Philadelphia: The Falcon Press, 1962. (Box 1)
    - Ronner, Heinz; Jhaveri, Sharad and Vasella, Alessandro. Louis I. Kahn, Complete Work 1935-1974. Zurich: Institute for the History and Theory of Architecture, The Swiss Federal Institute of Technology, 1977. (Box 1A)
  - Publications on/by Kahn
    - Entire issue devoted to Kahn, l'architecture aujourd'hui Louis I. Kahn february/march 1969. (Box 2)
    - Entire issue devoted to Kahn, Global Architecture, no date, no. 35 in a series. (Box 2)
    - "Louis I. Kahn Silence and Light," A&U Architecture and Urbanism. vol. 3, no date. (Box 2)
    - "The Room, the Street and Human Agreement," Louis I. Kahn. AIA Journal. september 1971, pp. 33-34. (Box 2)
    - "Louis Kahn's Yale University Centre for British Art and British Studies," Peer Smithson. RIBA Journal. april 1976, pp. 149-151. Yale Revue. 5 february 1975, p. 12. (Box 2)
    - "Architecture: Silence and Light," Louis I. Kahn. On the Future of the Art. New York: The Viking Press, 1970,pp. 21-35. (Box 2)
    - "How am I doing, wonder? Reflections on Louis Kahn," Richard Weinstein and Charles Moore. The New Journal. 22 april 1974, pp. 6-8. (Box 2)
    - "Quality shops planned for Mellon Center," The Yale Graduate/Professional. 24 January 1974, pp. 3 and 8. (Box 2)
    - "Mellon Center: Art Treasure..., Yale Daily News. 10 october 1973, p. 4. (Box 2)
    - "Louis I. Kahn, Foremost American Architect, Dies," Paul Goldberger; "Kahn's Buildings Blended Logic, Power and Grace," Ada Louise Huxtable, The New York Times, 21 march 1974, p. 46. (Box 2)
  - Books, publications of/by Louis Kahn:
    - The Architectural Review January 1974 (Box 3)
    - "The University Museum: Accidental past, purposeful future," John R. Spencer, Art in America, jul/aug 1971, pp. 84-90. (Box 3)
    - Modern Design and Construction. publication of the George B.H. Macomber Company, may 1969 and june 1973. (Box 3)
    - Global Architecture. Louis I. Kahn--Yale University Art Gallery and Kimbell Art Museum. 1976. (Box 3)
    - "Edison Price: his name is no accident," Stanley Abercrombie. Architecture Plus, august 1973, pp. 35-43. (Box 3)
    - "Louis Kahn: Greatest of His Time," The New Haven Register. 31 march 1974, p. F5. (Box 3)
    - "The Meaning of a Wall," Ada Louise Huxtable. The New York Times. 7 april 1974, no page number. (Box 3)
    - "Louis I. Kahn (1901-1974): education and inspiration," Vincent J. Scully, Jr., Yale Daily News. 15 april 1974, p. 2. (Box 3)
    - Almanac. The University of Pennsylvania, 26 march 1974, p. 2.Nilsson, Sten. The New Capitals of India, Pakistan and Bangladesh. Sweden: Scandinavian Institute of Asian Studies Monograph Series, 1973, pp. 183-219. (Box 3)
    - Carlo Scarpa. Exhibition, Royal Institute of British Architects. feb-apr 1974, poem by Louis Kahn prefaces catalogue. (Box 3)
    - Cook, John W. and Klotz, Heinrich. Conversation with Architects. New York: Praeger Publishers, 1973, pp. 178-219. (Box 3)
    - "The Architect and the Building," Bryn Mawr Alumnae Bulletin. summer, 1962, pp. 2-5. (Box 3)
    - "Architecture Alive on Campus: Erdman Hall," Bryn Mawr Alumnae Bulletin. fall 1965, pp. 2-9. (Box 3)
    - "Debts Imperil Future of Kahn's Archives," Paul Goldberger. The New York Times. 8 may 1974, no page number. (Box 3)
    - The Salk Institute. 1968. (Box 3)
    - "Postscript: Kahn, Penn and the Philadelphia School," Mimi Lobell, Oppositions 4. october 1974, pp. 63-64; "The Space Between," Alison and Peter Smithson, pp. 75-78. (Box 3)
    - Memorial to Louis I. Kahn 1901-1974, program for a tribute to Louis Kahn on 12 may 1974, copy of remarks by Jules D. Prown. (Box 3)
    - "Kahn: a singular passion for architecture," Carolynn Meinhardt, The Westsider. 28 march 1974, p. 8. (Box 3)
    - "The Museum Explosion," Douglas Davis. Newsweek. 17 september 1973, pp. 88-89. Louis I. Kahn, Architect. Richards Medical Research Building. Museum of Modern Art Bulletin, 1961. (Box 3)
    - "At the University," Scott R, Herhold, Yale Alumni Magazine. april 1972, pp. 30-31 Brawne, Michael. The New Museum. New York: Praeger Press, 1965, pp. 10, 14, 16, 20, 27, 133-134. (Box 3)
    - "Kahn," Norman Rice. Architecture. may/June 1974, pp. 102-107. (Box 3)
    - "British Center at Yale: End of the Beginning," Michael Lassell. The New Haven Register, 4 january 1976, pp. 1D and 4D. (Box 3)
    - L'héritage de Louis Kahn, Jacques Michel. Le Monde. 14 march 1975, p. 26. The American Academy of Arts and Letters and The National Institute of Arts and Letters Exhibition of work by newly elected members and recipients of honors and awards. may/june 1973. (Box 3)
    - Harrison, Laurence S. Report on the Deteriorating Effects of Modern Light Sources. no date. (Box 3)
    - Scully, Vincent, Jr. Louis I. Kahn. New York: George Braziller, 1962. Heimsath, Clovis. Pioneer Texas Buildings, A Geometry Lesson. Forward by Louis I. Kahn. Austin and London: The University of Texas Press, 1968. Bryan, James and Sauer, Rolf, eds. Structures Implicit and Explicit. Philadelphia: The Graduate School of Fine Arts, The University of Pennsylvania, 1973, pp. 158-161. (Box 3)
    - Proposals for the Library at the Phillips Exeter Academy. no date. Architecture. The John William Lawrence Memorial Lectures, The Tulane University School of Architecture. Louis Isadore Kahn, 1972. (Box 3)
    - Visionary Architects. The University of St. Thomas, Houston, 1968, pp. 9-10. Bulletin. Philadelphia Museum of Art. spring 1974, pp. 56-57. (Box 3)
    - Bulletin. Philadelphia Chapter, AIA. april 1974, pp. 2-7. Kahn. Louis I. Kahn: Talks with Students. Architecture at Rice 26. Rice University, 1969. (Box 3)
    - The Art of Design Management. The Tiffany/Wharton Lectures. New York: Tiffany & Co., 1975. (Box 3)
    - Xeroxes of a bibliography on Kahn (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous printed material by/about Louis Kahn, 1954, 1972-1978, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Photos
    - Exeter Library (Box 4)
    - Models of the British Art Centre (Box 4)
    - Hard hat tour of the BAC in construction: Mellon, Brewster and others. (Box 4)
    - Construction (Box 4)
    - Louis Kahn (Box 4)
    - Presentation drawing of skylight plan, BAC (Box 4)
    - Finished interior, BAC (Box 4)
    - Fourth floor elevator lobby and concrete stairwell (Box 4)
    - BAC site, October 1974 (Box 4)
    - BAC site, August 1972--first day of demolition (Box 4)
    - BAC site, July 1972 site before demolition and negatives. (Box 4)
    - Lighting study for skylight, Richard Kelly, 10 May 1973. (Box 4)
    - Interiors, lobbies, etc. (Box 4)
    - Reception desk, theatre, main entrance, stairwell, detail: door, walls. (Box 4)
    - Second floor reference library (Box 4)
    - Assorted dignitaries on hard hat tour: Mellon, Kahn Brewster, others. (Box 4)
    - Presentation drawings: (Box 4)
    - Basement (Box 4)
    - East-west section (Box 4)
    - Fourth floor (Box 4)
    - Section/elevation (Box 4)
    - North-south section (Box 4)
    - Basement plan (Box 4)
    - Street-floor plan (Box 4)
    - Second-floor plan (Box 4)
    - Library (Box 4)
    - Floorplans, elevation (Box 4)
    - Presentation drawings (Box 4)
    - Transmittal letters from Pellecchia and Meyers to Marnie Halsey and E.P. Pillsbury, giving figures for final building footage. (Box 4)
    - 1970 photos of Plans for BAC (Box 4)
    - First project roof garden and court, 24 september 1970 (Box 4)
    - First project drawings (Box 4)
    - architectural drawings (not photos) of sales desk, letters from Pellechia and Meyers to Marnie Halsey and Professor William Jordy of Brown University. (Box 4)
    - Site photos: (Box 4)
    - 3 November 1972 (Box 4)
    - 1 December 1972 (Box 4)
    - 2 January 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1 February 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1 March 1973 (Box 4)
    - 5 April 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1 June 1973 (Box 4)
    - 2 July 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1 August 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1 September 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1 October 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1 November 1973 (Box 4)
    - December 1973 (Box 4)
    - 15 January 1974 (Box 4)
    - 1 February 1974 (Box 4)
    - 6 March 19714 (Box 4)
    - 3 April 1974 (Box 4)
    - 1 May 1974 (Box 4)
    - 4 June 1974 (Box 4)
    - 1 July 1974 (Box 4)
    - 1 August 1974 (Box 4)
    - 3 October 1974 (Paul Mellon and Kingman Brewster) (Box 4)
    - 11 December 1974 (interiors) (Box 4)
    - 6 January 1975 (Box 4)
    - 10 February 1975 (Box 4)
    - 4 March 1975 (Box 4)
    - 4 April 1975 (Box 4)
    - 1 May 1975 (Box 4)
    - 4 June 1975 (Box 4)
    - 10 June 1975 (Box 4)
    - 1 July 1975 (Box 4)
    - 1 August 1975 (Box 4)
    - 4 September 1975 (Box 4)
    - 1 October 1975 (Box 4)
    - 4 November 1975 (Box 4)
    - 5 December 1975 (Box 4)
    - 6 January 1976 (lecture hall outdoor court) (Box 4)
    - Small color photos--construction, Paul Mellon and Louis Kahn with Kingman Brewster and others. (Box 4)
    - Photos 16 september 1975, visit to BAC by Paul Mellon and Edward Heath. (Box 4)
    - Contact sheets--hard hat tour, Paul Mellon and Kingman Brewster 11 april 1974 (Box 4)
    - Mellon visit october 1974 (Box 4)
    - Mellon visit with Jules Prown, 1 march 1975 (Box 4)
    - Louis Kahn (Box 4)
  - Photos and xeroxes
    - Photographs: sketches by Louis Kahn of plans for the BAC (Box 5)
    - Photographs and photocopies: Skylight details, sections, elevation, roof plans, floor plans (Box 5)
    - Photographs of second project sketches and plans, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Stair and court (Box 5)
      - Book display areas (Box 5)
      - Fourth floor galleries (Box 5)
      - Drawing of library spaces (Box 5)
      - Transverse section through court, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - Transverse section through central hall, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - Transverse section through lecture hall, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - Longitudinal section through center of building, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - Longitudinal section through galleries, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - Roof plan, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - Fourth floor plan, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - Second floor plan, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - Second floor mezzanine plan, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - Third floor plan, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - First floor mezzanine plan, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - First floor plan, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - Basement floor plan, 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - West elevation, 1971 March 3 (Box 5)
      - Elevation renderings, Circa 1971 March 8 (Box 5)
      - Drawing of display galleries (Box 5)
      - Isometric sketch of galleries (Box 5)
      - Drawing of gallery space (Box 5)
      - Sketch of gallery space (Box 5)
      - Models, interior and exterior, BAC (Box 5)
      - Skylight, construction, roof detail, wall, ceiling molding detail (Box 5)
    - Unidentified sketches by Louis Kahn (four black/white), 1973, undated (Box 5)
- Additional Material, 1951 April 28; Accession 2005-M-008
  Scope and Contents
  Also includes Accession 2006-M-003
  - Black ink sketch signed and dated by Louis Kahn [possibly entitled "A Religious Place"], 1951 April 28 (Box 1)
  - Six black and white photographs of the National Assembly complex in Dakha, Bangladesh, signed by Louis Kahn, 1undated (Box 1)